Guide to the Peter Diamond Papers, 1963-2013 RL.10164
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Peter Diamond papers
1963-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Diamond, Peter A.
RL.10164
5 Linear Feet 3,750 items
Peter A. Diamond is an Institute Professor at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), where he has taught since 1966. He was awarded the 2010 Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Science. The Peter Diamond papers date from 1963 to 2013 and document Diamond's career as a renowned economist whose work has focused on U.S. Social Security policy and other forms of social insurance. The collection's materials cover Diamond's writings, grants, and participation in lectures, seminars, and other events, as well as Diamond's association with groups such as the National Science Foundation (NSF), the American Association of Retired Persons (AARP), and the National Academy of Social Insurance (NASI).
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
Provenance
The Peter Diamond Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
Biographical Note
Peter A. Diamond is an Institute Professor at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, where he has worked since 1966. Diamond received a B.A. in mathematics from Yale University in 1960 and a Ph.D. in economics from MIT in 1963. Diamond has been a visiting professor at universities across the world, including Churchill College in Cambridge, U.K. and Harvard University. He has served as a member on panels at the National Academy of Sciences, the U.S. Senate, and the Massachusetts Legislature. Diamond is the author of twelve books and more than one hundred articles, most of which focus on pension reform, U.S. Social Security policies, and other issues in social insurance. He is a recipient of the 2010 Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Science for his work on social insurance and equilibrium theory.
Collection Overview
The Peter Diamond papers document Diamond's career as a prominent economist. Materials in the collection date from 1966 to 2013, with the highest concentration of documents from 1986 to 1998. The various manuscripts, books, journal articles, letters, and other resources document Diamond's writing, publication, and grant-writing activities during his years teaching at the University of California-Berkeley and MIT, his prepared testimony for the committees within the U.S. House of Representatives and the U.S. Senate's Committee on Finance, and his engagement with various groups and institutions.
The Printed Materials series contains four subseries. The first, Journal Articles, includes original copies and reprints of Diamond's writing for publications. The Working Papers subseries contains Diamond's preliminary papers which were intended to be shared with colleagues for further discussion. The third subseries, Books and Chapters, includes copies of Diamond's books and photocopied or printed chapters from his contributions to edited volumes, or chapters by other economists. The final subseries, Pamphlets, includes bound copies of Diamond's testimony, a Report to the U.S. Department of Labor, Pension, and Welfare Benefits Programs, and Diamond's chapter in a pamphlet commemorating his receipt of the 2010 Nobel Prize.
The Drafts series encompasses a number of draft versions of Diamond's various papers and articles, revised in preparation for lectures and publications. These drafts often reflect Diamond's continued work on a project over a span of years.
The Events series contains Diamond's lectures, presented to institutions like Harvard University and The Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, agendas from meetings such as 2009's Discussing Pension Reform in China in Bejing, and various materials from NSF-NBER and other conferences and seminars.
The Correspondence series includes a small amount of Diamond's correspondence, much of which is letters to and from journals between 1966 and 1968, and with the National Academy of Social Insurance (NASI).
The Research Notes series contains Diamond's handwritten notes, transparencies, and different charts and graphs created in preparation for his writings and lectures.
Diamond, Peter A.
- Printed Materials, 1966-2013, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains four subseries. The first, Journal Articles, includes original copies and reprints of Diamond's writing for publications such as the American Economic Journal, the Journal of Public Economics, and the Journal of Political Economy, among others. The Working Papers subseries contains Diamond's preliminary papers which were intended to be shared with colleagues for further discussion. These working papers treat topics such as "Universal Group Health Insurance: Another Approach" and "Unemployment and Vacancies in Steady State Growth," in addition to others. The third subseries, Books and Chapters, includes copies of Diamond's books and photocopied or printed chapters from his contributions to edited volumes, or chapters by other economists. The final subseries, Pamphlets, includes bound copies of Diamond's testimony, a Report to the U.S. Department of Labor, Pension, and Welfare Benefits Programs, and Diamond's chapter in a pamphlet commemorating his receipt of the 2010 Nobel Prize.
  Arrangement note
  The documents in the Journal Articles subseries are organized chronologically. Working Papers, Books and Chapters, and Pamphlets subseries are arranged by title.
  - Journal Articles, 1964-2006 and undated, 44 folders
    - Journal articles (Box 1)
  - Working Papers, undated
    - Neokeynesian Distribution: An Empirical Application (Box 1)
    - Search, Sticky Prices, and Inflation with Consumer Differences (Box 1)
    - On the Asset Demand for Money (Box 1)
    - The Future of Social Security (Box 1)
    - Pricing and the Distribution of Money Holdings in a Search Economy (Box 1)
    - Disembodied Technical Change in a One Sector Model (Box 1)
    - Savings Decisions under Uncertainty (Box 1)
    - Identification of the Elasticity of Substitution and the Rise of Technical Change (Box 1)
    - Integrating Punishment and Efficiency Concerns for Punitive Damages, for Reckless Disregard of Risks to Others (Box 1)
    - Integrating Allocation and Stabilization Budgets (Box 1)
    - Insulation of Pensions from Political Risk (Box 1)
    - Rational Expectations Business Cycles in Search Equilibrium (Box 1)
    - Risk Aversion and Savings (Box 1)
    - Efficiency Effects of Punitive Damages (Box 1)
    - The Economics of Social Security Reform (Box 1)
    - Administrative Costs and Equilibrium Charges with Individual Accounts (Box 1)
    - Optimal Taxation and Public Investment (Box 1)
    - Reforming Pensions (Box 1)
    - Reforming Public Pensions in the U.S. and the U.K. (Box 1)
    - Pensions for an Aging Population (Box 1)
    - Reducing Benefits and Subsidizing Individual Accounts (Box 1)
    - Social Security Investment in Equities (Box 1)
    - Toward an Optimal Social Security Design (Box 1)
    - Ranking, Unemployment Duration, and Wages (Box 1)
    - "Equilibrium without an Auctioneer" in Advances in Economic Theory (1987) (Box 1)
    - Neo Keynesian Distribution: An Empirical Application, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Books and Chapters
    - "On Contingent Valuation Measurement of Nonuse Values" in Contributions to Economic Analysis, 1993 (Box 1)
    - "On the Political Economics of Trade: Notes of a Social Insurance Analyst", 1996 (Box 1)
    - "Optimal Tax Theory and Development Policy: Directions for Future Research" (Box 1)
    - "Pricing and the Distribution of Money Holdings in a Search Economy" in New Approaches to Monetary Economics (Box 1)
    - "Social Security Reforms" in The Chilean Economy: Policy Lessons and Challenges (Box 1)
    - "Measurement of the Elasticity of Factor Substitution and Bias of Technical Change" in Production Economics: A Dual Approach to Theory and Applications (Box 1)
    - "Integration Allocation and Stabilization Budgets" (Box 1)
    - "Insulation of Pensions from Political Risk" in The Economics of Pensions (Box 1)
    - "Taxation and Public Production in a Growth Setting" (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      2 copies.
    - Social Security Reform, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Uncertainty in Economics: Readings and Exercises, 1978, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Taxation, Incomplete Markets, and Social Security, 2005 (Box 2)
    - On Time: Lectures on Models of Equilibrium, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Saving Social Security: A Balanced Approach, 2004 (Box 2)
    - Reforming Pensions: Principles and Policy Choices, 2008 (Box 2)
    - A Search-Equilibrium Approach to the Micro Foundations of Macroeconomics: The Wicksell Lectures, 1982, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Pension Reform: A Short Guide, 2010 (Box 2)
      By Nicholas Barr and Peter Diamond.
    - Scientists, Engineers, and Medical Doctors in Turkey: A Human Rights Mission, 2013 (Box 2)
      A Report to the International Human Rights Network of Academies and Scholarly Societies. Carol Corillon, Peter Diamond, Hans-Peter Zenner.
    - Income Security and Health Care: Economic Implications 1991-2010: An Expert Panel Report to the Advisory Council on Social Security (Box 2)
      Panel chaired by Peter Diamond.
    - Progettare un buon sistema pensionistico, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets, 1998-2010 and undated
    - The Future of Social Security for this Generation and the Next: Proposals Regarding Personal Accounts. Testimony before the U.S. House of Representatives, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Report of the Consultant Panel on Social Security to the Congressional Research Service, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Pension Reform Phase II in Retired State, County and Municipal Employees Association of Massachusetts, 2009 (Box 4)
    - U.S. Senate Committee on Finance: Report of the Panel on Social Security Financing (Box 4)
    - "Unemployment, Vacancies, Wages" in Les Prix Nobel, 2010 (Box 4)
    - National Academy of Social Insurance: Evaluating Issues in Privatizing Social Security (Box 4)
    - "Retirement Savings and Behavior" Report to the U.S. Department of Labor, Pension, and Welfare Benefits Programs (Box 4)
    - Economic Globalisation and Swedish Pensions, 2009 (Box 4)
      Expert Report No. 28 to Sweden's Globalisation Council.
    - Unemployment and Wages: What have we learned from the European experience?, 1990 (Box 4)
      Olivier Jean Blanchard and Peter Diamond.
- Drafts, 1963-2008, 1 box
  This series encompasses a number of draft versions of Diamond's various papers, revised in preparation for lectures and publications. Drafts include preparation for articles such as "Husband and Wife Age Differences and Social Security" (1982) and "How to Keep Social Security Out of Trouble" (1972), among many others. These drafts often reflect Diamond's continued work on a project over a span of years.
  Folders in the Drafts series are organized by date and title.
  Access Restrictions
  Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
  - Inventories and Money Holdings in a Search Economy (Box 3)
  - Public Finance Theory -Then and Now (Box 3)
  - Economic Efficiency with Some Irrationality (Box 3)
  - Financial Crisis in Benefit Cost Analysis (Box 3)
  - Pairwise Credit in Search Equilibrium (Box 3)
  - Financial Issues in Benefit Cost Analysis (Box 3)
  - Productivity, 1963 (Box 3)
  - A Note on Criteria for Public Investment by Daniel McFadden, 1968 (Box 3)
  - External Diseconomies in Competitive Supply, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Legal Rules and Resource Allocation, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Insurance and Taxation with Individual Uncertainty: The Uniform Case, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Social Security: Benefits and Taxes, 1978 (Box 3)
  - How to Keep Social Security out of Trouble, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Efficient Contracting in Mortensen's Model of the Matching Process, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Individual Savings Benefits, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Social Security: A Case for Changing the Earnings Test but Not the Normal Retirement Age, 1980 (Box 3)
  - An Example of Aggregate Demand Management in Search Equilibrium, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Search Equilibrium, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Husband-Wife Age Differences and Social Security, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Cost of Living Adjustments of Social Security Benefits, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Indexing Cost of Living Adjustments, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Adjusting One's Standard of Living II: Continuous Time, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Discussion of "Saving Behavior" by M. King, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Optimal Tax Theory and Development Policy-Directions for Future Research, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Externalities and Efficiency in a Model of Stochastic Job Matching, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Economic Aspects of Optimal Disability Benefits, 1984, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Search Theory, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Ignorance and Monetary Policy, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Equilibrium without an Auctioneer, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Rational Expectations Business Cycles in Search Equilibrium, 1985-1987 (Box 3)
  - Rational Expectations Business Cycles in Search of Equilibrium: A Correction digital files, 1989, Disk image generated from a 3.5" floppy disk. Approximately 1.44 megabytes.
    Digital files include control code written in C as well as a text file describing the applications.
  - Credit in Search Equilibrium, 1985, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Pricing and the Distribution of Money Holdings in a Search Economy, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Stochastic Credit in Search Equilibrium, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Optimal Taxation and the Le Chatelier Principle, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Unemployment and Vacancies in Steady State Growth, 1988 (Box 3)
  - A Proposal for Universal Coverage through Compulsory Group Health Insurance, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Organizing the Health Insurance Market, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Does Contingent Valuation Measure Preferences? Experimental Evidence, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Universal Group Health Insurance: Another Approach, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Search, Sticky Prices, and Deflation, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Search, Sticky Prices, and Deflation digital files, 1989
  - Ranking, Unemployment Duration, and Wages, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Privatization of Social Security, 1993, 1995, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Discussion of the Conceptual Underpinnings of the Contingent Valuation Method by A.C. Fisher, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Lectures on Models of Equilibrium, 1994 (Box 3)
  - The Health Reform Debate in the U.S., 1994 (Box 3)
  - On the Political Economy of Trade: Notes of a Social Insurance Analyst, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Economic Support in Old Age, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Integration of Eligibility Ages in Social Security Benefit Calculations, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Public Provisions of Pensions, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Ranking, Unemployment Duration, and Training Costs, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Zero Interest and Discount Rate Example, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Optimal Income Taxation: An Example with a U-Shaped Pattern of Optimal Marginal Tax Rates, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Horizontal Equity, Ideal Taxation, and Optimal Taxation, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Deadweight Burden Measurement in an Intertemporal Setting, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Managerial Incentives: On the near Linearity of Optimal Compensation, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Feldstein's Social Security Plan, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Evaluating Issues in Social Security Privatization, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Vicarious Liability for Punitive Damages, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Quasi-Hyperbolic Discounting and Retirement, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Efficiency Effects of Punitive Damages, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Benefits and Retirement Age, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Integrating Punishment and Efficiency Concerns for Punitive Damages, for Reckless Disregard of Risks to Others, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Optimal Tax Treatment of Private Contributions for Public Goods with and without Warm Glow Preferences, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Efficiency with Nonrational Defendants: Punitive and Vicarious Punitive Damages, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Comments on the Proposed Rules for Natural Resource Damage Assessments: A Submission to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Money Illusion, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Evaluating Social Security Reform Proposals (Box 3)
  - Notes on Inflationary Distortions and Taxes by Martin J. Bailey (Box 3)
  - The Phillips Curve and the Beveridge Curve digital files, 1988-1989, Disk images derived from two 5.25" floppy diskettes. Approximately 700 kilobytes.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous digital files, 1985 and 1989, Disk images generated from two 5.25" floppy disks. Approximately 700 kilobytes.
    Includes scripts, BASIC files, and other data files. Emulated DOS environments may render these, but they are unusable in current Windows platforms.
  - Equilibrium Under Uncertainty, undated (Box 6)
  - A Note on the Effects Upon the Distribution of Income of a Tight Money Policy, by O. Brownlee and A. Conrad, undated (Box 6)
  - Note on the Concept of Risk, undated (Box 6)
  - Productivity, 1963 (Box 6)
  - National Debt paper: correspondence and comments, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Criteria for Social Security, 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 6)
- Grants, undated, 1 box
  This series includes Diamond's proposals and other grant-related work.
  - "A Search Equilibrium Approach to the Micro Foundations of Macro," Proposal to the Sloan Foundation (Box 4)
  - "Uncertainty, Social Insurance, and the Micro Foundations of Microeconomics," Proposal to the National Science Foundation (NSF) (Box 4)
  - "Public Policy and Uncertainty," NSF (Box 4)
  - Social Insurance, NSF (Box 4)
  - Guggenheim and SSRC project proposals and correspondence, 1965-1966; 2 folders (Box 6)
- Events, 1973-2013, 1 box
  The Events series contains Diamond's lectures, presented to institutions like Harvard University and The Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, agendas from meetings such as 2009's Discussing Pension Reform in China in Bejing, and various materials from NSF-NBER and other conferences and seminars.
  The Event series is arranged by the title of the seminar, lecture, conference, etc.
  - Social Security Panel (Box 4)
  - Undated Lectures (Box 4)
  - Center on Budget and Policy Priorities and the Century Foundation, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Social Security Quotes Transparencies (Box 4)
  - Research Agenda on Pensions (Box 4)
  - "Comment on Arrow," Harvard Lecture (Box 4)
  - "Increases in Risk and in Risk Aversion," NSF-NBER Conference on Decision Rules (Box 4)
  - "Incentives and Information," First Berlin Symposium on Planning, 1973 (Box 4)
  - "Optimal Taxation of Identical Consumers when Markets are Incomplete," Public Finance Workshop, 1988 (Box 4)
  - "Search, Sticky Prices, and Inflation with Consumer Differences" Econometric Society Meeting, 1990 (Box 4)
  - "Pension Reform in a Transition Economy: Notes on Poland and Chile," NBER Conference on Industrial Restructuring in Eastern Europe, 1992 (Box 4)
  - "Issues in Social Insurance" Nancy L. Schwartz Memorial Lecture, 1993 (Box 4)
  - "On the Political Economy of Pensions and Social Security" Miami Seminar, 1994 (Box 4)
  - National Health Reform -Comment AEA Meeting, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Ad Hoc Faculty Committee on the Closing of CMRAE, 1994 (Box 4)
  - "Social Security Reform in the U.S.," IEA Congress, 1995 (Box 4)
  - "Economic Support in Old Age," Annual World Bank Conference on Development Economics, 1995 (Box 4)
  - "Macroeconomic Aspects of Social Security Reform," Brookings Panel on Economic Activity, 1997 (Box 4)
  - AARP Concord Coalition Debate on Social Security, 1998 (Box 4)
  - "The Economics of Social Security Reform," NASI Conference, "Framing the Social Security Debate," 1998 (Box 4)
  - Panel for Social Security Advisory Board, 2001 (Box 4)
  - "Evaluating the Report of President Bush's Commission to Strengthen Social Security," AEI, 2002 (Box 4)
  - "Social Security Reform and the President's Commission," AARP National Legislative Council, 2002 (Box 4)
  - "Cyclical Unemployment, Structural Unemployment" Lecture, 2013 (Box 4)
  - "Social Security, the Government Budget and National Savings," American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research, 2003 (Box 4)
  - "Savings and Portfolio Choice in a Two-Period, Two-Asset Model," Cowles Foundation at Yale University, 2000 (Box 4)
  - "Theory and Policy," World Bank Social Safety Nets Seminar, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Seminar on Discussing Pension Reform in China, 2009 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1966-2001, 1 box
  This series includes Diamond's correspondence with journals (primarily 1966 to 1968), the National Academy of Social Insurance (NASI), and various other individuals and groups.
  The Correspondence series is organized by the name of the entity with whom Diamond was corresponding.
  - 1966-2001 and undated (Box 4)
  - Email correspondence, 1999-2005, Two text files in MBOX format derived from a laptop's internal hard drive. Approximately 50 kilobytes.
  - Journal Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 4)
  - National Academy of Social Insurance, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Princeton and Stanford Psychology Departments, 1991-1995 (Box 4)
- Academia
  - Teaching Material, 1976-2013; 2 folders (Box 4)
    Contains images of slides, course notes, syllabi, problem sets, tests, and other teaching material.
  - Research Notes 1965-2001, 1 box
    The Research Notes series contains Diamond's handwritten and typed research notes, as well as a number of preparatory materials for various publications, including graphs and charts.
    The folders in the Research Notes series are arranged by date.
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Expenditure Functions and the Indirect Utility Function (1965) (Box 4)
    - 1977 (Box 4)
    - 1985 (Box 4)
    - 2003 (Box 4)
    - Social Security-Length of Career, 2008 (Box 4)
    - 2011 (Box 4)
  - Fiscal Economics lecture notes (course number 14.471 and 131B), 1966-1972 and undated; 10 Folders (Box 5)
  - Untitled lecture transcript, undated (Box 5)
  - Embodied rate of technical progress worksheets, undated (Box 5)
  - Research partnership with Tjalling C. Koopmans, Cowles Foundation, 1960 and undated; 3 folders (Box 6)
    Includes drafts, mathematical proofs, and correspondence on joint project "Allocations of Resources Over Time," include NSF grant materials. Many pages are on thermofax paper and have been photocopied at acquisition for preservation pf content.